<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: common sense | Coding Libetartian]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.stevemoyer.net/blog/categories/common-sense/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.stevemoyer.net/"/>
  <updated>2013-03-12T16:01:23-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.stevemoyer.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Steve Moyer]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Freeway Driving]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.stevemoyer.net/2010/08/09/freeway-driving.html"/>
    <updated>2010-08-09T22:20:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.stevemoyer.net/2010/08/09/freeway-driving</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class='post'>
<div xmlns='http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml'><p>As a software developer it amazes me how many software developers simply go on doing what they've been doing without making any attempt to grow or improve. At some point I hop in the car and begin the drive home. It doesn't take too long before I realize that it's not just developers. Many people can't be bothered to pay any attention to what they are doing in any setting. How many times during each trip do I come up behind someone in the fast lane (or carpool lane) going 10-20 miles per hour slower than majority of the traffic on the freeway. It's at this point that I begin to wonder why they are doing what they are doing. This list usually amounts to something like the following:</p><ol><li>They think it's ok because they are going the posted speed limit (or within some miles per hour of it)</li><li>They can't stand the thought of anyone going faster than them.</li><li>They're taking a moral stand against those going over the posted speed limit.</li><li>They like the far left lanes because there is never anyone close in front of them.</li><li>...</li></ol><p>As I get down the list, I realize that while there are some people who may identify with the reasons above, the majority of these people are likely just not paying any attention. They get on the freeway, merge over to the fast lane(s), and completely check out. They don't notice the large line of cars piling up behind then. They don't notice the frustrated people who resort to passing them in the slower lanes (at worst having to pass 2 or 3 lanes over). They've probably been driving many years and at no point have they noticed any of these things happening.</p><p>While I'm often happy to ridicule and mock them as we drive along, what I'd really like to do is lay it out for them:</p><p><span style=' font-size:large;'><strong>You are creating traffic</strong></span></p><p>As the cars pile up behind you the amount of congestion is increasing. Two cars driving slowly in the wrong lanes can just about block the entire freeway. Everyone else will be delayed because of you.</p><p><span style=' font-size:large;'><strong>You aren't gaining anything</strong></span></p><p>If you just move a few lanes over you can still go the same speed without blocking anyone.</p><p><span style=' font-size:large;'><strong>You are creating a traffic hazard</strong></span></p><p>As cars rapidly approach from behind you they find themselves with the choice to either pass on the slow side or sit in congestion behind you. In either case you are causing the freeway to be less safe than it should be.</p><p><span style=' font-size:large;'><strong>Here are a few simple easy to follow rules</strong></span></p><ol><li>If you can't talk and drive at the same time you either a) don't talk or b) don't drive. Take your pick.</li><li>You should drive in the slowest lane that can contain your speed.</li><li>Should the need to pass arise you need to pass in a reasonable fashion. Speed up at least 5 miles per hour faster than the person you are passing. After completing the pass move back to the prior lane if it's safe to do so. If you can't pass at a difference of at least 5 miles per hour than you should slow down and stay behind the car until there is a point when you can.</li><li>If you aren't going faster than the regular traffic in the fast lanes you have absolutely no business in the carpool lane</li><li>If all of the lanes on the freeway are going a pace that is uncomfortable for you, perhaps you would be more comfortable on surface streets.</li><li>It is your job as a driver to know how many cars are in front of you and how far away they are, how many cars are behind you and how far away they are, what the pace of traffic is in the lanes to either side of you. If you don't know these things you are an unsafe driver. </li></ol><p><span style=' font-size:large;'><strong>So, what's the point?</strong></span></p><p>I'm sure that's more than enough of me ranting about oblivious freeway drivers. The same thing applies to software developers (and other team members). You may not be the best or fastest at what you do but it is your job to keep up with what other people are doing to be better and or faster. I'd hope that you're also trying to figure out how you could be better and or faster. Even if you aren't, the one thing you should make sure you aren't doing is holding back others or possibly even the entire team. One or two people clogging up the works is often enough to stall or seriously slow down even the most productive team. </p><p> </p></div></div>



]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Office Recycling]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.stevemoyer.net/2010/03/23/office-recycling.html"/>
    <updated>2010-03-23T20:30:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.stevemoyer.net/2010/03/23/office-recycling</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class='post'>
<div xmlns='http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml'>I'm noticing an annoying trend at the client locations where I've been working.  The number of recycling bins in the offices are sky-rocketing.  Why is this annoying you ask?  Don't you want to recycle?  Don't you care about the environment?<br/><br/>While I certainly have some thoughts about those last two questions, they aren't the reason for my post.  The reason for my annoyance is that the total number of bins hasn't changed.  Corresponding to the sky-rocketing number of recycle bins is a plummeting number of waste baskets.  In many of the offices I've been in lately desks and cubes each have their own recycling but there are only a few waste baskets.  The planners of this no doubt imagine that trouble finding a nearby waste basket will cause people to generate less waste.  Unfortunately, what actually happens is that people just start throwing their trash away in the recycle bins.  If the goal was to simply change the color of waste baskets to blue then congrats and mission accomplished.  If the goals was to get the recycling and trash separated by the people generating them then these efforts have failed miserably.  We're now at the same place we were 10 years ago, we can either pay people to separate the mixed trash and recycling or we can get cans side by side.  <br/></div></div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Beyond Business Casual]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.stevemoyer.net/2010/01/23/beyond-business-casual.html"/>
    <updated>2010-01-23T03:38:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.stevemoyer.net/2010/01/23/beyond-business-casual</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class='post'>
As in "There is no good reason to go beyond business casual".  For some reason many individuals and companies have decided that the more dressed up a person is correlates positively with how much they have to offer as well as how productive an employee they are.

I would argue that where you dress on the scale (from anywhere above a greasy stained t-shirt up to a basic suit) indicates almost nothing.  I wouldn't mark someone down for dressing at the level required by their company's dress code but I would say that dressing above what is required is correlated negatively with skills and positively with the playing politics.  If we lived in the land of Pride and Prejudice this would all make sense but shouldn't we have moved beyond using this kind of thing as a proxy with which to measure people.

There's a reason all politicians and many sales people wear suits all the time.  They literally have nothing of value to offer.  When this is the case, it makes sense for them as individuals to spend all of their time trying to give the false impression that they are powerful and important.  Isn't it time we stopped buying into it?

They always have their excuses.  I have to keep up with the competition.  First impressions are important.  Shaking hands and kissing babies isn't as great for my image if I'm not dressed to the nines.  How about developing a real value proposition?  When I run into companies who are unusually casual for their industry(WAMU, Southwest Airlines for example) I often find that they are known for lower prices and friendlier service. 

I fairly consistently push the lower boundaries of the dress codes wherever I go.   I applaud people like my co-worker who showed up to work in a plain white t-shirt and jean shorts this past Friday.  Assuming you aren't wearing a bikini or mankini the odds are good that nobody will question you.  If someone does, you either need to make yourself more valuable to the company or find a place to work with fewer folks who think that dress codes add value.</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
