<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Libertarianism | Coding Libetartian]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.stevemoyer.net/blog/categories/libertarianism/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.stevemoyer.net/"/>
  <updated>2013-03-21T13:43:56-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.stevemoyer.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Steve Moyer]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Free State]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.stevemoyer.net/2008/05/19/free-state.html"/>
    <updated>2008-05-19T13:43:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.stevemoyer.net/2008/05/19/free-state</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class='post'>
In the past year or so I've been aware of the <a href="http://freestateproject.org/">Free State Project</a>.  If it were somewhere other than New Hampshire I'd have to give it some serious thought(no offense to New Hampshire but I like warm weather and beaches). I think it's an interesting concept and it's led to me thinking about how effective it could be and how a true free state(as in nation state) might be created.  The problem I have with the FSP(other than the location issues) is that there's a preset limit on it's effectiveness.

As good as the state can get I'm pretty sure the US government would not allow it secede from the US.  The consequences of this are that the US government still gets it's cut of personal and business income off of the top and the state is still subject to US Federal Law.  If there's a supreme court ruling or constitutional amendment  to abolish abortion or outlawing gay marriage nation-wide NH Would still be forced to follow these rules.

Given the threat of a successful libertarian state to the US governments coffers, I'm fairly certain politicians, in their own interests, would have strong incentives to penalize the state as much as possible.  For example the government passes a law, if you don't have government run schooling you don't get federal road funding.  I'm pretty sure this is a law the unions could get behind.   Perhaps this is not the most reasonable example but in this particular example that has the state paying twice for both schooling and roads(because you know the us govt is not going to exempt the state from taxation for either).

I'm pretty sure there's no decent spot on the planet left to create a new country(and I'm pretty sure if there was, 20000 libertarians wouldn't have much luck getting control of it.  Is there another answer?</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
