<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: consulting | Coding Libetartian]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.stevemoyer.net/blog/categories/consulting/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.stevemoyer.net/"/>
  <updated>2013-03-14T11:53:41-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.stevemoyer.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Steve Moyer]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Consulting Engagement Success Indicators]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.stevemoyer.net/2010/03/29/consulting-engagement-success.html"/>
    <updated>2010-03-29T23:05:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.stevemoyer.net/2010/03/29/consulting-engagement-success</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class='post'>
<div xmlns='http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml'>Whenever I roll on to a new client there are a few things that I find to be leading indicators for the success of the engagement.<br/><ul><li>How long it takes to get a badge/computer/access to the building.  Hopefully this stuff is ready and waiting when you arrive. I have seen cases where a badge takes a few weeks and a computer takes up to two months.  It's particularly awesome if they won't provide you with a computer and won't allow your computer on their network.  If I don't have all of this stuff by the end of the first week on the client it's a bad sign.    <br/></li><li>The amount of time it takes before I hear the first mention of filing a ticket.  Something like "Here is your laptop, if you want a mouse or keyboard file a separate ticket for each and we'll get them for you."  I've really come to hate the words "file a ticket", particularly when preceded by "I forgot to" and followed by "so that won't be ready for a few weeks."</li><li>Availability of client personnel.  If the people I'm supposed to be working with are MIA or are splitting time with a bunch of other projects I lose a bit of confidence.  <br/></li></ul>I used to have a few more which seem to have slipped my mind.  Do you have any other early indicators for project/engagement success or failure? <br/> <br/></div></div>



]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
